<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-02-28T14:55:32+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Big Data Analytics Summer School 2019</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Welcome to Jekyll!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/10/21/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome to Jekyll!" /><published>2018-10-21T10:12:11+02:00</published><updated>2018-10-21T10:12:11+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/10/21/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/10/21/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;You’ll find this post in your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;jekyll serve&lt;/code&gt;, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To add new posts, simply add a file in the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_posts&lt;/code&gt; directory that follows the convention &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext&lt;/code&gt; and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;puts&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Hi, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;print_hi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;'Tom'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/docs/home&quot;&gt;Jekyll docs&lt;/a&gt; for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll&quot;&gt;Jekyll’s GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. If you have questions, you can ask them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://talk.jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll Talk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">You’ll find this post in your _posts directory. Go ahead and edit it and re-build the site to see your changes. You can rebuild the site in many different ways, but the most common way is to run jekyll serve, which launches a web server and auto-regenerates your site when a file is updated. To add new posts, simply add a file in the _posts directory that follows the convention YYYY-MM-DD-name-of-post.ext and includes the necessary front matter. Take a look at the source for this post to get an idea about how it works. Jekyll also offers powerful support for code snippets: def print_hi(name) puts &quot;Hi, #{name}&quot; end print_hi('Tom') #=&amp;gt; prints 'Hi, Tom' to STDOUT. Check out the Jekyll docs for more info on how to get the most out of Jekyll. File all bugs/feature requests at Jekyll’s GitHub repo. If you have questions, you can ask them on Jekyll Talk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">September 4th - September 8th 2017.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/090817" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="September 4th - September 8th 2017." /><published>2017-09-08T17:36:27+02:00</published><updated>2017-09-08T17:36:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/090817">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configured cluster network for 10gig networking&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planned out future experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup spark 2.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Attended class&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Created a script for automatically loading tmux workspace&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Planned future of SOCC Paper for next two months.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started new experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-general-note&quot;&gt;A General Note&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m finally back in the hang of things. I have to apologize that my website postings have been non-existant lately since I was on internship this summer at IBM Research. Now that I am back in Amherst and have started the new semester, I hope to start up again with new weekly updates. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;socc-paper&quot;&gt;SOCC Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our SOCC paper was rejected this summer, as such we have to make some changes and find a new place to submit to. We have settled on Eurosys for now, which gives us a little under two months to pull things together. We decided to make the entire paper use 10gig networking rather than the half 1gig half 10gig setup we had earlier. This will make the paper a lot stronger and hopefully confuse less reviewers. We also met this week to discuss some revisions to the experiments. A few of the reviewers complained that our workloads are not representative of real world data centers. We completely agree and are working towards trying to find more realistic scenarios we can evaluate. We are going to try and run a more realistic spark workload and a third workload that you may find in production. We also decided to rerun all previous experiments so that htey represent a 10gig network. Hopefully we’ll be able to pull together a nice overview of MPTCP in the datacenter for Eurosys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;classes&quot;&gt;Classes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Classes have started again much to my chagrin. This semester I am taking two cores in hopes of making up for some screw ups last year. I settled on taking an introduction to Logic course and a course on Visual Analytics. Introduction to logic seems like it will be useful but as it is more math based I may struggle a bit. Hopefully I’ll be able to work through it though and actually pick up the material. Visual Analytics is something I am very interested in and excited to learn more about. My research does a lot of measurement based work and I always find it difficult deciding on the best way to present results. I am hoping visual analytics will teach me a thing or two about the right way to present large data sets. I’ll try to update my weekly logs with some of the stuff I’m learning as it applies to my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;measurement-platform&quot;&gt;Measurement Platform&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of my summer work was looking at scaling containers and measuring performance. It gave me some ideas on how I can improve my experimental process to be more efficient. I am currently thinking of building a system that allows me to launch monitoring agents that measure performance of the system and then automatically cleans and presents the data in a nice format. A lot of this is built off of my summer work but I am hoping to write it in a new way so that it is more robust and multi-purpose. I hope to eventually use this system when running my many experiments in the future. I’ll hopefully put up a full blog post on both how I run experiments and what this new system will do in a few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;First homework assignments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finishing up re-running 10gig experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Architecting new experiments to round out the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SEC ‘17 Slide for the October Conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Configured cluster network for 10gig networking Planned out future experiments Setup spark 2.0 Attended class Created a script for automatically loading tmux workspace Planned future of SOCC Paper for next two months. Started new experiments A General Note I’m finally back in the hang of things. I have to apologize that my website postings have been non-existant lately since I was on internship this summer at IBM Research. Now that I am back in Amherst and have started the new semester, I hope to start up again with new weekly updates. Stay tuned! Weekly Summary SOCC Paper Our SOCC paper was rejected this summer, as such we have to make some changes and find a new place to submit to. We have settled on Eurosys for now, which gives us a little under two months to pull things together. We decided to make the entire paper use 10gig networking rather than the half 1gig half 10gig setup we had earlier. This will make the paper a lot stronger and hopefully confuse less reviewers. We also met this week to discuss some revisions to the experiments. A few of the reviewers complained that our workloads are not representative of real world data centers. We completely agree and are working towards trying to find more realistic scenarios we can evaluate. We are going to try and run a more realistic spark workload and a third workload that you may find in production. We also decided to rerun all previous experiments so that htey represent a 10gig network. Hopefully we’ll be able to pull together a nice overview of MPTCP in the datacenter for Eurosys. Classes Classes have started again much to my chagrin. This semester I am taking two cores in hopes of making up for some screw ups last year. I settled on taking an introduction to Logic course and a course on Visual Analytics. Introduction to logic seems like it will be useful but as it is more math based I may struggle a bit. Hopefully I’ll be able to work through it though and actually pick up the material. Visual Analytics is something I am very interested in and excited to learn more about. My research does a lot of measurement based work and I always find it difficult deciding on the best way to present results. I am hoping visual analytics will teach me a thing or two about the right way to present large data sets. I’ll try to update my weekly logs with some of the stuff I’m learning as it applies to my work. Measurement Platform Part of my summer work was looking at scaling containers and measuring performance. It gave me some ideas on how I can improve my experimental process to be more efficient. I am currently thinking of building a system that allows me to launch monitoring agents that measure performance of the system and then automatically cleans and presents the data in a nice format. A lot of this is built off of my summer work but I am hoping to write it in a new way so that it is more robust and multi-purpose. I hope to eventually use this system when running my many experiments in the future. I’ll hopefully put up a full blog post on both how I run experiments and what this new system will do in a few weeks. What’s up for next week? First homework assignments Finishing up re-running 10gig experiments Architecting new experiments to round out the paper. SEC ‘17 Slide for the October Conference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">March 27th to May 8th, 2018</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/050517" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="March 27th to May 8th, 2018" /><published>2017-05-07T17:36:27+02:00</published><updated>2017-05-07T17:36:27+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/050517">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submitted MPTCP Migration Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submitted MPTCP Summary Paper&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished AI&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Returned to Containers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-general-note&quot;&gt;A General Note&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last month and a half has been quite hectic. I had several deadlines and enough coursework to keep me busy. As such I was unable to keep up with my weekly posts. This entry will serve as a general overview of the significant tasks for this time period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mptcp-migration-paper&quot;&gt;MPTCP Migration Paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting reject from its first submission, we did some tailoring and reworked the paper so that we could submit again. It should hopefully be a little bit clearer and stronger. We reworked several of the graphs to be more clear and rephrased paragraphs to better get our point across. We also removed a section that felt quite random. Hopefully it does well this round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mptcp-summary-paper&quot;&gt;MPTCP Summary paper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We recently submitted an MPTCP paper that will serve to be our concluding work on the topic. It was quite a quick turnaround on the paper but we were able to get it submitted on time despite having an impossible AI exam in the way. I’m quite happy with the writing and think it is quite strong but not everyone is so confident. Hopefully things go smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;finished-ai&quot;&gt;Finished AI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally finished my AI course. Its been a rough semester overall especially towards the end. I ended up having the worst grade in the class on one of the homeworks. It was quite discouraging, but I tried to not let it bother me. I studied quite a lot for the final but it was a rough exam! Unfortunately, I discovered MIt’s lecture notes on the topic too late. They seem to explain things in a much clearer way for the style that I learn. If I have to take the course again at least I will be more prepared!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;containers-again&quot;&gt;Containers Again&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that the MPTCP work is over, I’m thinking of switching back to containers for a bit. My internship seems to have some overlap with my previous containers work, so I plan to spend the next few weeks catching up on container work and preparing for that. I’m starting by working my way through some containers papers and using our remaining Azure credits to run a kubernetes cluster. I’m excited to get some experience with the platform.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Submitted MPTCP Migration Paper Submitted MPTCP Summary Paper Finished AI Returned to Containers A General Note The last month and a half has been quite hectic. I had several deadlines and enough coursework to keep me busy. As such I was unable to keep up with my weekly posts. This entry will serve as a general overview of the significant tasks for this time period. Summary MPTCP Migration Paper After getting reject from its first submission, we did some tailoring and reworked the paper so that we could submit again. It should hopefully be a little bit clearer and stronger. We reworked several of the graphs to be more clear and rephrased paragraphs to better get our point across. We also removed a section that felt quite random. Hopefully it does well this round. MPTCP Summary paper We recently submitted an MPTCP paper that will serve to be our concluding work on the topic. It was quite a quick turnaround on the paper but we were able to get it submitted on time despite having an impossible AI exam in the way. I’m quite happy with the writing and think it is quite strong but not everyone is so confident. Hopefully things go smoothly. Finished AI I finally finished my AI course. Its been a rough semester overall especially towards the end. I ended up having the worst grade in the class on one of the homeworks. It was quite discouraging, but I tried to not let it bother me. I studied quite a lot for the final but it was a rough exam! Unfortunately, I discovered MIt’s lecture notes on the topic too late. They seem to explain things in a much clearer way for the style that I learn. If I have to take the course again at least I will be more prepared! Containers Again Now that the MPTCP work is over, I’m thinking of switching back to containers for a bit. My internship seems to have some overlap with my previous containers work, so I plan to spend the next few weeks catching up on container work and preparing for that. I’m starting by working my way through some containers papers and using our remaining Azure credits to run a kubernetes cluster. I’m excited to get some experience with the platform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">March 20th - March 24th 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/032017" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="March 20th - March 24th 2017" /><published>2017-03-24T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-24T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/032017">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Picked up new switches&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configure one switch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replaced dead switch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compile list of probing tools&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Experiment Design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Workload Scripting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started script building for experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Registered for NSDI ‘17&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Debugged spark a little bit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spark&quot;&gt;Spark&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I returned back to spark to see if we could find any new insights. When we looked a little closer at the terasort results, we saw that a lot of the time was being held up by the save to disk portion of the workload. We tuned the workload so that instead we just count the results. This allowed us to see clearly for the computation stage what the two protocols were doing. We thought we then received encouraging results but instead it looks like things turn quite variable. We will run more runs later to see if we can tease out the properties of each protocol for the workload.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-switches&quot;&gt;New Switches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new switches finally arrived on Tuesday. I picked them up from cscf and brought them over to our server room. Because they are half rack switches we don’t quite have the right mounting equipment. As such we can’t setup the switches just yet. I did set up one switch just to play around with. They are quite easy to manage with a nice webui although unfortunately we can’t modulate the network speeds as much as we thought. We have only two basic options which are auto and 100mbit/s. We were hoping for somethign in between 100mbit and 1G. We will have to find another way to modulate the traffic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of switches, the day after we hooked up the new switch, our management switch for our mini-edge cluster died on us. It was a very old switch and I saw this coming from a mile down the road since after the last power outage it wouldn’t come back on until we manually intervened. Luckily we had a spare 1gig switch and I quickly replaced it to get some of the machine back online. We unfortunately had to leave some of them offline because the 1gig switch only has 8 ports. I plan to bring in another 8port switch next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;list-of-network-tools&quot;&gt;List of Network Tools&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of our experimentation process we need to find a way to understand exactly what is going on under the hood when we run MPTCP and TCP. This week I started compiling a list of available tools and the stats they provide so when we want to see a specific behavior we can easily find the right tool to acquire the data. This list is not complete nor is it long, but it is a start. I hope to post it in the resources section when I get a free moment. I will update back here when I get a chance to post it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;experiment-design&quot;&gt;Experiment Design&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we have a bunch of experiments to run with a bunch of different conditions, I dedicated a bunch of time this week to planning out all the experiments and conditions using my experimental documentation format. This format basically outlines what our hypothesis is, what the experiment does, what should our graphs show and what monitoring should be done. We also list the configuration of all machines and networking options. It also contains the procedure for replication as well as the eventual results and a brief analysis. The goal is to provide a comprehensive overview of each experiment so we know exactly what was done to achieve each result. I spent a large part of this week preparing these sheets for the different experiments we are planning on running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;experiment-scripting&quot;&gt;Experiment Scripting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday I started scripting our first experiment. The script will gather all the configuration details for each machinem, will start the monitors, run the experiment and then clean up afterwards. This will hopefully remove alot of the manual details so we can easily run the experiment multiple times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nsdi-17&quot;&gt;NSDI ‘17&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This years NSDI is in Boston, which happens to be just down the road. As an impromptu decision a bunch of us decided to go last minute. Next Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday I will be in Boston attending the conference. Hopefully I will get to talk to some people with more MPTCP experience to get their feelings on the protocol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NSDI ‘17&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MPTCP Profiling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start disk experiments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Picked up new switches Configure one switch Replaced dead switch Compile list of probing tools AI Homework Experiment Design Workload Scripting Started script building for experiments Registered for NSDI ‘17 Debugged spark a little bit Weekly Summary Spark On Monday, I returned back to spark to see if we could find any new insights. When we looked a little closer at the terasort results, we saw that a lot of the time was being held up by the save to disk portion of the workload. We tuned the workload so that instead we just count the results. This allowed us to see clearly for the computation stage what the two protocols were doing. We thought we then received encouraging results but instead it looks like things turn quite variable. We will run more runs later to see if we can tease out the properties of each protocol for the workload. New Switches The new switches finally arrived on Tuesday. I picked them up from cscf and brought them over to our server room. Because they are half rack switches we don’t quite have the right mounting equipment. As such we can’t setup the switches just yet. I did set up one switch just to play around with. They are quite easy to manage with a nice webui although unfortunately we can’t modulate the network speeds as much as we thought. We have only two basic options which are auto and 100mbit/s. We were hoping for somethign in between 100mbit and 1G. We will have to find another way to modulate the traffic. Speaking of switches, the day after we hooked up the new switch, our management switch for our mini-edge cluster died on us. It was a very old switch and I saw this coming from a mile down the road since after the last power outage it wouldn’t come back on until we manually intervened. Luckily we had a spare 1gig switch and I quickly replaced it to get some of the machine back online. We unfortunately had to leave some of them offline because the 1gig switch only has 8 ports. I plan to bring in another 8port switch next week. List of Network Tools As part of our experimentation process we need to find a way to understand exactly what is going on under the hood when we run MPTCP and TCP. This week I started compiling a list of available tools and the stats they provide so when we want to see a specific behavior we can easily find the right tool to acquire the data. This list is not complete nor is it long, but it is a start. I hope to post it in the resources section when I get a free moment. I will update back here when I get a chance to post it. Experiment Design Since we have a bunch of experiments to run with a bunch of different conditions, I dedicated a bunch of time this week to planning out all the experiments and conditions using my experimental documentation format. This format basically outlines what our hypothesis is, what the experiment does, what should our graphs show and what monitoring should be done. We also list the configuration of all machines and networking options. It also contains the procedure for replication as well as the eventual results and a brief analysis. The goal is to provide a comprehensive overview of each experiment so we know exactly what was done to achieve each result. I spent a large part of this week preparing these sheets for the different experiments we are planning on running. Experiment Scripting On Friday I started scripting our first experiment. The script will gather all the configuration details for each machinem, will start the monitors, run the experiment and then clean up afterwards. This will hopefully remove alot of the manual details so we can easily run the experiment multiple times. NSDI ‘17 This years NSDI is in Boston, which happens to be just down the road. As an impromptu decision a bunch of us decided to go last minute. Next Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday I will be in Boston attending the conference. Hopefully I will get to talk to some people with more MPTCP experience to get their feelings on the protocol. What’s up for next week? NSDI ‘17 MPTCP Profiling Start disk experiments</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">March 13th - March 17th 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/031317" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="March 13th - March 17th 2017" /><published>2017-03-13T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-13T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/031317">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performed Additional LAN VM Experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Performed ndiffports MPTCP experiments on Azure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigated Gitlab setup&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;MPTCP Buffer Formula Script&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;nsf-grfp&quot;&gt;NSF GRFP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was once again denied the NSF GRFP. While I am not upset about the outcome, I was a little disappointed reading the reviews. One in particular was rather harsh and seemed to be more attacking my skills as a graduate student rather than my application as a whole. That’s all I am going to reference on the issue. Onwards and upwards!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lan-vm-experiments&quot;&gt;LAN VM Experiments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran some brief experiments on our LAN cluster evaluating the performance of migrations in the LAN environment. The results were as expected where we were able to get roughly double the performance of tcp migrations. These were more for validation than anything else. It was good to see MPTCP succeed in one case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ndiffports-algorithm&quot;&gt;NDiffPorts Algorithm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of this week performing experiments on Microsoft Azure’s public cloud. I set up three virtual machine’s with two located in the same datacenter and a third on the west coast. I configured each machine to use mptcp and run with the ndiffports algorithm. Briefly, the ndiffports alogoirthm is designed for use with machines that only have one interface but may be located in a data center where multiple paths are available between switches due to ECMP. The algorithm creates several TCP sockets using different ports so that ECMP hashes them onto different ports. Unfortunately, for us we do not know for sure whether ECMP and multiple paths exist in Azure datacenters, so going into this experiment I was not hopeful. The results for this experiment were not encouraging. We were unable to get MPTCP’s performance to outperform TCP in either environment, despite tuning buffers and modifying the number of subflows. In every experiment, MPTCP lagged way behind TCP. This is likely due to multiple paths not existing between the machines as assumed. I was still rather shocked to see MPTCP do worse than baseline TCP. We are investigating further to see what we can find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that did result from these experiments was a discussion about which congestion control mechanism to use for MPTCP and TCP. We traditionally use Reno for TCP and Lia for MPTCP due to their similarties. We have to think about whether this is unfair, since I have seen cubic outperform Reno on several occassions. Does this mean we have unfairly hampered TCP? Decoupling MPTCP also seemed to have some performance benefits but what does that mean for other TCP connecitons on the machine. These are questions I hope to investigate going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;git-lab&quot;&gt;Git Lab&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lab recently deployed a gitlab server for our projects. It fell to me to evaluate the system and investigate how it works and what permissions to use. I spent about an hour and a half going through it and put together a brief one pager on some of the things we should consider as we use it in our lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mptcp-buffer-script&quot;&gt;MPTCP Buffer Script&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created a brief script to calculate the bandwidth delay product for MPTCP since it takes in a few different factors and units. Now I should be able to just enter the conditions and get the buffer size I need to configure the machine with. It is located in my SystemScripts repo under mptcp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan out how to trace some of the networking behavior we are seeing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read through the in-depth networking blog posts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hopefully deploy our new topology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Return to Spark and tune terasort parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Homework 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Performed Additional LAN VM Experiments Performed ndiffports MPTCP experiments on Azure Investigated Gitlab setup MPTCP Buffer Formula Script Weekly Summary NSF GRFP I was once again denied the NSF GRFP. While I am not upset about the outcome, I was a little disappointed reading the reviews. One in particular was rather harsh and seemed to be more attacking my skills as a graduate student rather than my application as a whole. That’s all I am going to reference on the issue. Onwards and upwards! LAN VM Experiments I ran some brief experiments on our LAN cluster evaluating the performance of migrations in the LAN environment. The results were as expected where we were able to get roughly double the performance of tcp migrations. These were more for validation than anything else. It was good to see MPTCP succeed in one case. NDiffPorts Algorithm I spent most of this week performing experiments on Microsoft Azure’s public cloud. I set up three virtual machine’s with two located in the same datacenter and a third on the west coast. I configured each machine to use mptcp and run with the ndiffports algorithm. Briefly, the ndiffports alogoirthm is designed for use with machines that only have one interface but may be located in a data center where multiple paths are available between switches due to ECMP. The algorithm creates several TCP sockets using different ports so that ECMP hashes them onto different ports. Unfortunately, for us we do not know for sure whether ECMP and multiple paths exist in Azure datacenters, so going into this experiment I was not hopeful. The results for this experiment were not encouraging. We were unable to get MPTCP’s performance to outperform TCP in either environment, despite tuning buffers and modifying the number of subflows. In every experiment, MPTCP lagged way behind TCP. This is likely due to multiple paths not existing between the machines as assumed. I was still rather shocked to see MPTCP do worse than baseline TCP. We are investigating further to see what we can find. One thing that did result from these experiments was a discussion about which congestion control mechanism to use for MPTCP and TCP. We traditionally use Reno for TCP and Lia for MPTCP due to their similarties. We have to think about whether this is unfair, since I have seen cubic outperform Reno on several occassions. Does this mean we have unfairly hampered TCP? Decoupling MPTCP also seemed to have some performance benefits but what does that mean for other TCP connecitons on the machine. These are questions I hope to investigate going forward. Git Lab Our lab recently deployed a gitlab server for our projects. It fell to me to evaluate the system and investigate how it works and what permissions to use. I spent about an hour and a half going through it and put together a brief one pager on some of the things we should consider as we use it in our lab. MPTCP Buffer Script I created a brief script to calculate the bandwidth delay product for MPTCP since it takes in a few different factors and units. Now I should be able to just enter the conditions and get the buffer size I need to configure the machine with. It is located in my SystemScripts repo under mptcp. What’s up for next week? Plan out how to trace some of the networking behavior we are seeing. Read through the in-depth networking blog posts. Hopefully deploy our new topology. Return to Spark and tune terasort parameters. AI Homework 3</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">March 6th - March 10th 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/2017/03/10/weekly.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="March 6th - March 10th 2017" /><published>2017-03-10T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-03-10T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/2017/03/10/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/2017/03/10/weekly.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ordered switches for edge cloud network&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup power management for edge cloud nodes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Synthesis Proposal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ran More Spark Experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Toured around a new faculty candidate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Exam&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-switches&quot;&gt;New Switches&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finally ordered new switches for our edge cloud network. This will allow us to build the proposed topology from a few week ago. We settled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdwg.com/shop/products/NETGEAR-M4300-12X12F-Managed-Switch-24x10G-12x10GBASE-T-12xSFP-XSM4324S/3993463.aspx?pfm=srh&quot;&gt;Netgear M4300&lt;/a&gt; hybrid switches which feature both 10G copper 
and 10G SFP+ with fallback to 1G for the copper side. These will hopefully allow us to use the same switch across the network whether we are using 10G or 1G networking. We will hopefully receive these in the next two weeks so 
we can get to work on evaluating the redundancy of MPTCP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;synthesis-proposal&quot;&gt;Synthesis Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At UMass instead of qualifying exams we are expected to complete a synthesis proposal that takes two areas of CS and combines in a project. Throughout this project you get to work with two faculty and do some “multi-disciplinary” work. The deadline for proposing a project was on Wednesday which means I spent the majority of the beginning
of this week working on the proposal. It was pretty straightforward and will hopefully be accepted. My proposal is combining Networking and Operating Systems through my MPTCP migration work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spark-experiments&quot;&gt;Spark Experiments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also spent part of this week tuning the shuffle parameters for Spark workloads. It was unfortunately all for nothing as I could not improve the performance no matter what I tuned. A closer look is needed, hopefully I can spend some time next week on this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;faculty-candidate&quot;&gt;Faculty Candidate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CICS had a prospective faculty candidate this week and I was tasked with making sure they got to their meetings on time. It was more difficult than I expected as each meeting seemed to start late and go way over the allotted time. It was enlightening experience as it demonstrated the hiring process at UMASS. I must say, it is a little overwhelming!
It was also a cool experience because I got to tour the human testing facility on campus. It was way cool! They have a full functioning apartment that they can use to monitor individuals as they go about their day. They also have two metabolic chambers which were quite impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-exam&quot;&gt;AI Exam&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thursday was the AI exam. It was not as bad as expected but as always I could have studied more! Here’s to hoping things went well!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;azure-experiments&quot;&gt;Azure Experiments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got it in my head that I would like to try to examine MPTCP’s ndiffports functionality since this is something we have largely ignored to now. I decided to test it out in the public cloud with Microsoft Azure’s Cloud Service. I tried to take the easy way out and install MPTCP on the VM’s with the ubuntu package manager but that did not seem to work. When I went to run MPTCP, none of the congestion control managers were installed! I ditched the package manager version and installed the kernel from scratch which took a significant amount of time. I ran out of time to run the actual experiments but to have them completed by early next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Investigate spark further&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finish the Azure Experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start some initial writing to get an idea of what we want to say/show.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Ordered switches for edge cloud network Setup power management for edge cloud nodes Synthesis Proposal Ran More Spark Experiments Toured around a new faculty candidate AI Exam Weekly Summary New Switches We finally ordered new switches for our edge cloud network. This will allow us to build the proposed topology from a few week ago. We settled on Netgear M4300 hybrid switches which feature both 10G copper and 10G SFP+ with fallback to 1G for the copper side. These will hopefully allow us to use the same switch across the network whether we are using 10G or 1G networking. We will hopefully receive these in the next two weeks so we can get to work on evaluating the redundancy of MPTCP. Synthesis Proposal At UMass instead of qualifying exams we are expected to complete a synthesis proposal that takes two areas of CS and combines in a project. Throughout this project you get to work with two faculty and do some “multi-disciplinary” work. The deadline for proposing a project was on Wednesday which means I spent the majority of the beginning of this week working on the proposal. It was pretty straightforward and will hopefully be accepted. My proposal is combining Networking and Operating Systems through my MPTCP migration work. Spark Experiments I also spent part of this week tuning the shuffle parameters for Spark workloads. It was unfortunately all for nothing as I could not improve the performance no matter what I tuned. A closer look is needed, hopefully I can spend some time next week on this. Faculty Candidate CICS had a prospective faculty candidate this week and I was tasked with making sure they got to their meetings on time. It was more difficult than I expected as each meeting seemed to start late and go way over the allotted time. It was enlightening experience as it demonstrated the hiring process at UMASS. I must say, it is a little overwhelming! It was also a cool experience because I got to tour the human testing facility on campus. It was way cool! They have a full functioning apartment that they can use to monitor individuals as they go about their day. They also have two metabolic chambers which were quite impressive. AI Exam Thursday was the AI exam. It was not as bad as expected but as always I could have studied more! Here’s to hoping things went well! Azure Experiments I got it in my head that I would like to try to examine MPTCP’s ndiffports functionality since this is something we have largely ignored to now. I decided to test it out in the public cloud with Microsoft Azure’s Cloud Service. I tried to take the easy way out and install MPTCP on the VM’s with the ubuntu package manager but that did not seem to work. When I went to run MPTCP, none of the congestion control managers were installed! I ditched the package manager version and installed the kernel from scratch which took a significant amount of time. I ran out of time to run the actual experiments but to have them completed by early next week. What’s up for next week? Investigate spark further Finish the Azure Experiments Start some initial writing to get an idea of what we want to say/show.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">February 27th to March 3rd 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/022717" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="February 27th to March 3rd 2017" /><published>2017-02-27T09:13:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-27T09:13:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/022717">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meeting with Prashant&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Candidates Friday&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Poster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spark Emulator&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week was a fairly busy one but not on the research end of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-homework&quot;&gt;AI Homework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next AI homework was due this week so I spent a significant amount of time on Thursday trying to complete that homework. I unfortunately did not finish the homework. You win some you lose some.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meeting-with-prashant&quot;&gt;Meeting with Prashant&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met with Prashant to discuss the current state of affairs. We are thinking about writing a negative result paper with MPTCP since it seems like no matter what we do we can not get mptcp to work with some workloads. So we may write a paper classifying workloads and describing why MPTCP can or can not help. We also will include the redundancy benefits of MPTCP as a positive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;candidates-friday&quot;&gt;Candidate’s Friday&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year we have an open house for new Phd candidates to explore the department and meet professors and current students. It’s a big event and one of my favorite times of the year. This year I’m hosting three students. I spent a lot of this week preparing for this Friday, so research kind of fell by the way side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;research-poster&quot;&gt;Research Poster&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for Friday, Prashant asked me to build a poster to showcase my research, and I do love building posters, so he did not have to ask me twice! I constructed a more general poster on edge clouds as a concept rather than a detailed research poster. I hope to post it soon. This poster will also serve as a good visual for when we have visitors and I need to explain my research to them. I might post it on the wall outside our lab since that seems to be rather barren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;//docs.google.com/viewer?url=http://mrlucasch.github.io/research/edge_cloud.pdf?dl=0&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;embedded=true&quot; class=&quot;gde-frame&quot; style=&quot;width:100%; height:800px; border: none;&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;spark-emulator&quot;&gt;Spark Emulator&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday, I tried running a spark shuffle emulator with larger flight sizes on our cluster. That failed in specatular fashion. It almost immediately crashes some of the machines. I am currently investigating what the cause is and will update this post as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New Spark Experiments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;VM migrations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tracing with Spark&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks AI Homework Meeting with Prashant Candidates Friday Poster Spark Emulator Weekly Summary This week was a fairly busy one but not on the research end of things. AI Homework The next AI homework was due this week so I spent a significant amount of time on Thursday trying to complete that homework. I unfortunately did not finish the homework. You win some you lose some. Meeting with Prashant I met with Prashant to discuss the current state of affairs. We are thinking about writing a negative result paper with MPTCP since it seems like no matter what we do we can not get mptcp to work with some workloads. So we may write a paper classifying workloads and describing why MPTCP can or can not help. We also will include the redundancy benefits of MPTCP as a positive. Candidate’s Friday Every year we have an open house for new Phd candidates to explore the department and meet professors and current students. It’s a big event and one of my favorite times of the year. This year I’m hosting three students. I spent a lot of this week preparing for this Friday, so research kind of fell by the way side. Research Poster In preparation for Friday, Prashant asked me to build a poster to showcase my research, and I do love building posters, so he did not have to ask me twice! I constructed a more general poster on edge clouds as a concept rather than a detailed research poster. I hope to post it soon. This poster will also serve as a good visual for when we have visitors and I need to explain my research to them. I might post it on the wall outside our lab since that seems to be rather barren. Spark Emulator On Monday, I tried running a spark shuffle emulator with larger flight sizes on our cluster. That failed in specatular fashion. It almost immediately crashes some of the machines. I am currently investigating what the cause is and will update this post as necessary. What’s up for next week? New Spark Experiments VM migrations Tracing with Spark</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">February 20th to February 24th 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/022017" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="February 20th to February 24th 2017" /><published>2017-02-24T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-24T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/022017">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Established a new productivity workflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Received new workstation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ran increasing file transfer experiment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ran terasort at 240gb and 100gb&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Met with Don&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Yoga!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup Entrepreneurship List Serve&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HDFS Memory Mount Experiment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-productivity-workflow&quot;&gt;New Productivity Workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I regularly run into an awesome student in the CS Lab who is currently in the process of 
finishing her Phd while also balancing a start up. We always have some really fascinating discussions.
This week we discussed the Getting Things Done methodology. I had previously heard of it but every
time I tried it out, I dropped it really quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out I was doing it wrong and only scratching the surface of it! I decided to take a crack
at it armed with a new tool to facilitate organization. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nirvanahq.com/&quot;&gt;Nirvanahq&lt;/a&gt; is a 
platform that allows you to implement the GTD methodology with minimal hassle. I have already seen 
an uptick in my productivity. I will provide more updates as the year progresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-workstation&quot;&gt;New workstation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received my new workstation this week! It’s a shiny 15” Macbook Pro w/ touchbar. This thing is amazing!
The screen alone is a massive upgrade from my macbook air. I spent some time this week getting the machine all configured and 
organized. Unfortunately, I spent all Thursday building an emulator on my macbook air and when I went into work on Friday with only 
my new machine, all my code was stuck at home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mptcp-file-transfer-experiment&quot;&gt;MPTCP File Transfer Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is commonly known that MPTCP performs poorly with short flows and as such we were curious to see at what point MPTCP
overtakes TCP when transferring files. We performed a brief experiment (~not up to peer review standards!) where we ran file transfers of varying sizes between two mptcp machines.
Our saw that around 100mb is when MPTCP overtakes TCP. This is likely because it is large enough that the time to transfer is longer than it takes to establish the subflows and exit slow-start. 
Unfortunately, this may be bad for us as the workload we run on spark performs many transfers of size 50mb so MPTCP is actually hampering performance slightly. We are going to try and perform and emulation
of the workload to see if this is truly the case. Hopefully next week will have those results so we can make an informed decision on the type of workloads we want to focus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;entrepreneurship-list-serve&quot;&gt;Entrepreneurship List Serve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another student(the same student who introduced me to GTD) and I decided that we should try to encourage more work at CICS in fostering entrepreneurship so we decided to start an internal list serve 
for students to discuss such topics. I spent some time this week signing people up and maintaining said list. The hope is that students will see how cool their research is and how easy it can be to turn 
that into a company. Hopefully good things will come of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hdfs-memory-experiment&quot;&gt;HDFS Memory Experiment&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the first read through of one of the papers we are using to guide our experiments with MPTCP I missed the fact that they mount half of their RAM as a tempfs for HDFS. They use this as the 
tmp location for HDFS to eliminate disk related bounds. I attempted to do something similar by running terasort on a smaller workload (100gb vs 240gb) since we only had 32gb to mount vs the papers 64gb.
The results from these experiments were inconclusive as they were close to the non tmpfs results. This may be due to other optimizations the original paper performed that were not mentioned such as disabling
swap or something. I am going to keep digging deeper to see what I can unearth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;yoga&quot;&gt;Yoga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t entirely research related, but I started doing yoga this week at my climbing gym. They offer a 6:45 am (holy cow batmam, that’s early!) Good Morning Vinyasa class free to members. It was amazing 
and very relaxing. It was a great way to start the morning and I hope it will serve to keep my head clear in the future so I can get more research done! I recommend other grad students give it a try, since
most students seem to always be in a perpetual state of stress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run Shuffle Emulator&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TCP Probe w/ terasort&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identiyfy new workloads with our desired properties&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Candidate Friday Prep&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Established a new productivity workflow Received new workstation Ran increasing file transfer experiment Ran terasort at 240gb and 100gb Met with Don Yoga! Setup Entrepreneurship List Serve HDFS Memory Mount Experiment Weekly Summary New Productivity Workflow I regularly run into an awesome student in the CS Lab who is currently in the process of finishing her Phd while also balancing a start up. We always have some really fascinating discussions. This week we discussed the Getting Things Done methodology. I had previously heard of it but every time I tried it out, I dropped it really quickly. It turns out I was doing it wrong and only scratching the surface of it! I decided to take a crack at it armed with a new tool to facilitate organization. Nirvanahq is a platform that allows you to implement the GTD methodology with minimal hassle. I have already seen an uptick in my productivity. I will provide more updates as the year progresses. New workstation I received my new workstation this week! It’s a shiny 15” Macbook Pro w/ touchbar. This thing is amazing! The screen alone is a massive upgrade from my macbook air. I spent some time this week getting the machine all configured and organized. Unfortunately, I spent all Thursday building an emulator on my macbook air and when I went into work on Friday with only my new machine, all my code was stuck at home! MPTCP File Transfer Experiment It is commonly known that MPTCP performs poorly with short flows and as such we were curious to see at what point MPTCP overtakes TCP when transferring files. We performed a brief experiment (~not up to peer review standards!) where we ran file transfers of varying sizes between two mptcp machines. Our saw that around 100mb is when MPTCP overtakes TCP. This is likely because it is large enough that the time to transfer is longer than it takes to establish the subflows and exit slow-start. Unfortunately, this may be bad for us as the workload we run on spark performs many transfers of size 50mb so MPTCP is actually hampering performance slightly. We are going to try and perform and emulation of the workload to see if this is truly the case. Hopefully next week will have those results so we can make an informed decision on the type of workloads we want to focus on. Entrepreneurship List Serve Another student(the same student who introduced me to GTD) and I decided that we should try to encourage more work at CICS in fostering entrepreneurship so we decided to start an internal list serve for students to discuss such topics. I spent some time this week signing people up and maintaining said list. The hope is that students will see how cool their research is and how easy it can be to turn that into a company. Hopefully good things will come of this. HDFS Memory Experiment On the first read through of one of the papers we are using to guide our experiments with MPTCP I missed the fact that they mount half of their RAM as a tempfs for HDFS. They use this as the tmp location for HDFS to eliminate disk related bounds. I attempted to do something similar by running terasort on a smaller workload (100gb vs 240gb) since we only had 32gb to mount vs the papers 64gb. The results from these experiments were inconclusive as they were close to the non tmpfs results. This may be due to other optimizations the original paper performed that were not mentioned such as disabling swap or something. I am going to keep digging deeper to see what I can unearth. Yoga This isn’t entirely research related, but I started doing yoga this week at my climbing gym. They offer a 6:45 am (holy cow batmam, that’s early!) Good Morning Vinyasa class free to members. It was amazing and very relaxing. It was a great way to start the morning and I hope it will serve to keep my head clear in the future so I can get more research done! I recommend other grad students give it a try, since most students seem to always be in a perpetual state of stress. What’s up for next week? Run Shuffle Emulator TCP Probe w/ terasort Identiyfy new workloads with our desired properties AI Homework Candidate Friday Prep</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">February 13th to February 17th 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/021317" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="February 13th to February 17th 2017" /><published>2017-02-17T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-17T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/021317">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AI Homework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluated Switches to order for mptcp work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Racked Servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Networked Servers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Read some modeling papers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup server for health project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Established dates for IBM internship&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Met with Don and Prashant about MPTCP work&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Converted videos for the CS677 course&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;delayed-opening&quot;&gt;Delayed Opening&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last weekend we had quite a bit of snow fall, by my estimates over 15 inches. As a result, Monday morning was a delayed opening. This was a nice way to start the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ai-homework&quot;&gt;AI Homework&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent most of the first half of this week catching up on my AI homework that was due on Tuesday the 14th. It was a problem set on heuristic search. While an interesting subject I failed to leave myself enough time to get all the way through it. I managed to complete a solid 85% of the homework. Hopefully I do better on the next assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;don-and-prashant-meeting&quot;&gt;Don and Prashant Meeting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;dl class=&quot;wp-caption aligncenter&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 600px&quot;&gt;

&lt;dt&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;/images/obelix_top.png&quot; alt=&quot;Our New Topology&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dt&gt;

&lt;dd&gt;Our New Topology&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I met with Don and Prashant to discuss the status of our MPTCP work and in which direction to proceed. We discussed different directions and decided to divide my time between the modeling work for edge clouds and the spark data center experiments. We finally decided on a topology that looks like the picture above. We use simple 1g switches and then aggregate them with 2 10gig switches. The redundant paths should hopefully allow MPTCP to function at its best and improve some of our research. We agreed to try and replicate some of the experiments in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.usenix.org/node/196353&quot;&gt;IBM HotCloud’16&lt;/a&gt; paper about Spark and the [Ir]relevance of network bounds. We also briefly discussed some possible resources for the modeling work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-servers-saga&quot;&gt;New Servers Saga&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The saga with the new servers continues. I was able to rack the servers on Wednesday in a little under an hour which is a new record. I hooked up one server so that our group can use it for an unrelated health project until their server comes in. On Thursday, I got impatient waiting on our new switches, so I ventured back to the server room and hooked up the rest of the machines. I hooked up 8 servers directly to the main cluster network and then used two 8 port 1G switches to connect their two secondary interfaces. I also configured the servers with the MPTCP routing tables, and configurations we normally use. I went back to my old system admin toolbelt and brought out tmux-cssh to configure the machines. It’s a tool that opens up terminals on all the machines and then runs the same command on each one. I was able to configure the machines in way less time!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mptcp&quot;&gt;MPTCP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the week, I began running experiments on our spark infrastructure. I started with PageRank but a single run over the 1G livejournal dataset took over an 3 hours. Due to a lack of large shuffle phases, I decided to move on to the next workload. I decided on TeraSort and was able to successfully complete a 20G Terasort quite easily. With the test case out of the way. I moved onto a larger data set that resembled the workload in the IBM paper. As of this post, it is still running. I will provide an update on the results next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;misc&quot;&gt;Misc&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I settled on dates for my Internship at IBM Research. It appears that I will be at IBM from May 22nd to August 18th. Here’s to a summer in New York!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run some of the experiments from the IBM paper.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finish putting together presentation on the modeling notes from YC&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate possible future directions for the mptcp work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks AI Homework Evaluated Switches to order for mptcp work Racked Servers Networked Servers Read some modeling papers Setup server for health project Established dates for IBM internship Met with Don and Prashant about MPTCP work Converted videos for the CS677 course Weekly Summary Delayed Opening Last weekend we had quite a bit of snow fall, by my estimates over 15 inches. As a result, Monday morning was a delayed opening. This was a nice way to start the week. AI Homework I spent most of the first half of this week catching up on my AI homework that was due on Tuesday the 14th. It was a problem set on heuristic search. While an interesting subject I failed to leave myself enough time to get all the way through it. I managed to complete a solid 85% of the homework. Hopefully I do better on the next assignment. Don and Prashant Meeting Our New Topology I met with Don and Prashant to discuss the status of our MPTCP work and in which direction to proceed. We discussed different directions and decided to divide my time between the modeling work for edge clouds and the spark data center experiments. We finally decided on a topology that looks like the picture above. We use simple 1g switches and then aggregate them with 2 10gig switches. The redundant paths should hopefully allow MPTCP to function at its best and improve some of our research. We agreed to try and replicate some of the experiments in the IBM HotCloud’16 paper about Spark and the [Ir]relevance of network bounds. We also briefly discussed some possible resources for the modeling work. New Servers Saga The saga with the new servers continues. I was able to rack the servers on Wednesday in a little under an hour which is a new record. I hooked up one server so that our group can use it for an unrelated health project until their server comes in. On Thursday, I got impatient waiting on our new switches, so I ventured back to the server room and hooked up the rest of the machines. I hooked up 8 servers directly to the main cluster network and then used two 8 port 1G switches to connect their two secondary interfaces. I also configured the servers with the MPTCP routing tables, and configurations we normally use. I went back to my old system admin toolbelt and brought out tmux-cssh to configure the machines. It’s a tool that opens up terminals on all the machines and then runs the same command on each one. I was able to configure the machines in way less time! MPTCP Towards the end of the week, I began running experiments on our spark infrastructure. I started with PageRank but a single run over the 1G livejournal dataset took over an 3 hours. Due to a lack of large shuffle phases, I decided to move on to the next workload. I decided on TeraSort and was able to successfully complete a 20G Terasort quite easily. With the test case out of the way. I moved onto a larger data set that resembled the workload in the IBM paper. As of this post, it is still running. I will provide an update on the results next week. Misc I settled on dates for my Internship at IBM Research. It appears that I will be at IBM from May 22nd to August 18th. Here’s to a summer in New York! What’s up for next week? Run some of the experiments from the IBM paper. Finish putting together presentation on the modeling notes from YC Evaluate possible future directions for the mptcp work.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Start Date to End Date</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/020117" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start Date to End Date" /><published>2017-02-06T16:36:27+01:00</published><updated>2017-02-06T16:36:27+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/weekly-template</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/notebook/weekly/020117">&lt;h1 id=&quot;accomplished-tasks&quot;&gt;Accomplished Tasks&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;weekly-summary&quot;&gt;Weekly Summary&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;this-weeks-results&quot;&gt;This week’s Results&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;whats-up-for-next-week&quot;&gt;What’s up for next week?&lt;/h1&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Accomplished Tasks Weekly Summary This week’s Results What’s up for next week?</summary></entry></feed>